Boker tov בוקר טוב, Boker tov, happy Lag BaOmer ל"ג בעומר Lag
BaOmer everyone I guess.
Funny that the 34th of the Omer עומר Omer according to many
is the real day that's supposed to be a yom tov יום
טוב yom tov type of day. Anyway, also today we finished the
fourth perek פרק, perek, which is only four-tenths of the perakim פרקים,
perakim, but it is half of the masechet מסכת masechet in daphim
דפים. daphim. So for those that have been struggling with Eruvin עירובין,
Eruvin, you should know we're hitting the halfway point. All right, anyway,
we pick up three lines from the top.
Where were we? I'm sorry, no, we pick up with four lines
from the top. Amar Rami Bar Chama אמר רמי בר חמא. Amar
Rami Bar Chama. So Chama is from the first word of the
fifth line.
So we had been talking about the whole issue of the debate
of Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה,
Rabbi Yehuda, where if you don't use bread and you just are
physically present, whether that works. Rabbi Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
it only works for an ani עני ani and Rabbi Yehuda רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it works for an ani עני ani or
an ashir עשיר. ashir. We are defining ani עני ani as somebody
who is starting not from home, and an ashir עשיר ashir somebody
who is starting from home and therefore has accessible to them some
food to use. That's point number one. And number two, so Rabbi
Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says only for the guy caught out
on the street and Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it's
for anyone that you don't need to use bread. But the Gemara
גמרא Gemara said that that is a debate when you are actually
physically present at the spot you want to start Shabbos שבת, Shabbos,
tehei shvisasi bimkomi תהא שביתתי במקומי. tehei shvisasi bimkomi. But if you
actually want to do the special case of the mishnah משנה, mishnah,
to designate a spot away from you that maybe in theory you
could get to before it gets dark, but it's like a spot
that's a good deal away from you, that everybody agrees is only
for the ani עני, ani, is only for the person starting outside
of the house and caught without bread. That's going to be relevant
for the next mishnah משנה mishnah as well. But when you're starting
in the spot that you want to be, there it's debated Rabbi
Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
and we pasken פוסקן pasken like Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that anybody can do it, can start Shabbat שבת Shabbat without bread
if they want to start where they are physically present. Okay, so
now the Gemara גמרא Gemara just wraps this up. Amri Rami Bar
Chama אמרי רמי בר חמא, Amri Rami Bar Chama, harei amru הרי
אמרו, harei amru, they said Shabbat שבת, Shabbat, if somebody actually begins
Shabbos שבת Shabbos where they are, right, this exact case of Rabbi
Meir רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and Rabbi Yehuda רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda,
says where I'm standing should be where I begin Shabbat שבת, Shabbat,
yesh lo arba amot יש לו ארבע אמות, yesh lo arba amot,
four amot אמות. amot. Now what does that mean? It doesn't mean
only four amot אמות. amot. It means, and this was alluded to
before, we've spoken about 2004. It means where you start you draw
your square of four amot אמות. amot. It's debated if you remember
whether it's two whether it's you're in the middle of a four
by four square, at the edge of a four by four square,
maybe it's an eight by eight square. Whatever it is, we'll say
it's a square four by four that surrounds you. Let's assume you're
in the middle of it. Okay, that you get you begin with
that, that's your space plus 2000 amot אמות amot outside of that
space. So actually you get 2004 amot אמות. amot. That's when you
start it where you are physically present. Okay, now, hanosayn es eiruvo
הנתן
את עירובו, hanosayn es eiruvo, let's say you actually are not physically
present, the classic case of leaving your loaf of bread at some
spot. Yesh lo arba amot o lo יש לו ארבע אמות או
לא Yesh lo arba amot o lo? Do you measure four amot
אמות amot around that loaf of bread and then 2000 amot אמות
amot from the edges of that four amot אמות? amot? Or do
you measure 2000 amot אמות amot from that loaf of bread? Okay,
so it's a good question, right, we're always talking 2000, 2000, but
now we're finding out maybe it's first your four, like the same
way first it's your city and then it's 2000 outside of the
city. So if you don't start in a city, maybe it's first
your four amot אמות amot and then 2000 outside. Is it true
by bread the same way it's true when you are there physically?
So the Gemara גמרא Gemara says, amar Rava
אמר רבא, amar Rava, says Rava רבא, Rava, ta shma תא שמע,
ta shma, come and hear, lo amru me'arvin bepat ela lehakeil al
he'ashir, shelo yeitzei beraglav לא אמרו מערבין בפת אלא להקל על העשיר
שלא יצא ברגליו. lo amru me'arvin bepat ela lehakeil al he'ashir, shelo
yeitzei beraglav. Our mishnah משנה mishnah says that the whole purpose of
bread was not to demand bread, but to make it easier for
somebody that in theory that if they wanted to use bread, they're
ashir עשיר, ashir, they have the ability to use bread, they're starting
from home. They could do that and sit in their place. But
so they made it to be easier on you not to demand
it, the ability to use bread. So the whole point is using
a bread is a kula קולא. kula. Ve'im amarta ein lo ואם
אמרת אין לו, Ve'im amarta ein lo, and if you say however
if you use bread, you don't have a four ama אמה ama
square to begin with, hai lehakeil? lehachmir hu האי להקל להחמיר הוא
hai lehakeil? lehachmir hu! So you're not being lenient on the guy
letting them use bread, there's a cost to it. The cost is
that you only get 2000 amot אמות, amot, not four plus 2000.
So since the mishnah משנה mishnah says the use of bread is
a leniency, presumably there is no way in which it is more
detrimental to you than if you had done it in person. So
the Gemara גמרא Gemara says no, that really is not a good
point. Afilu hachi אפילו הכי, Afilu hachi, even if you would not
get the four amot אמות amot to begin with, nicha lei ki
haychi delo nitrach ve'neifak ניחא ליה כי היכי דלא ניטרח וניפוק. nicha
lei ki haychi delo nitrach ve'neifak. Overwhelmingly it's still a benefit. You
don't have to go to the effort to go out there physically
and be present yourself. You can send someone out there and stay
at home and you can just nobody has to wait till it
gets dark. So that is a big leniency even if it comes
with a potential little cost of not getting four amot אמות amot
around it and only getting 2000 amot אמות amot without the additional
four. So the Gemara גמרא Gemara does not have a conclusion whether
when you use the bread you start with a four ama אמה
ama square, but at least when you are with your person you
do start with a four ama אמה ama and then. the
same way when you're in a city, you start with the city
and then do the two thousand אמות amot outside of the city.
So before we get to the next משנה, mishna, just to you
know review one or two points from yesterday which are very key
because it's a revising of the numbers we use that we use.
So we normally speak about two thousand אמות, amot, but now we're
finding out that it's two thousand אמות, amot, well first of all
we always knew outside of your city, but even if you're there,
even if you start outside the city, it's two thousand אמות amot
outside of a four אמה ama square, and that's certainly true if
you're there in person maybe even with your bread. Also, it's debated
is it a four אמה, ama, four by four אמה ama square
or an eight by eight אמה ama square, are you in the
middle? And then just also to repeat some of the radical sort
of point that was made yesterday, which is the idea that you
square it off. What are the implications of that? So presumably it
means that, and we're going to see that coming up in the
beginning of the next פרק, perek, that when it comes to תחומים
techumim purposes, you square, you create a square based on the compass
points. So wherever you are or your city, you make a square
based on the compass points and then you make a two thousand
from there. So it's a two thousand by two thousand, actually bigger
based on your four אמות amot or your city, all squared off
based on the compass points. That's going to be extremely relevant, but
also what the גמרא Gemara says, it spoke about using a square
when it comes to carrying four אמות amot in רשות הרבים reshut
harabbim or רשות היחיד reshut hayachid being four טפחים. tefachim. And there
were a couple of opinions about that, I just also want to
repeat this again because it's just so radical and so different than
what we've been talking about for a מסכת masechet and a half.
One opinion is that carrying four אמות amot never really means four
אמות, amot, it always means the diagonal of a four by four
אמות, amot, which means carrying in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim is always
five point six אמות, amot, which is crazy, we always talk about
four אמות. amot. A more reasonable position of that, which is I
said yesterday this was רבנו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, actually this is the
position that argues on רבנו תם. Rabbeinu Tam. רבנו תם Rabbeinu Tam
says you always go by the diagonal, says that an object is
always seen to be in a four by four אמה ama square,
again defined by the compass points, assuming that's due north etc. And
therefore you're חייב chayav when you carry in רשות הרבים reshut harabbim
by taking it out of its space. So if you take it
out directly due north it's four אמות. amot. If you take it
out at an angle, at a forty five degree angle from where
from the compass points directly northeast or southwest or whatever, then it
would be five point six. But conceptually the idea of carrying four
אמות amot is not just the distance you've traveled but removing it
from its place, which is something we very much have seen in
discussions of carrying, the idea of having a place. And similarly by
a רשות היחיד reshut hayachid which is four טפחים tefachim by four
טפחים, tefachim, some say it never really means four טפחים, tefachim, it
really means five point six, it's always the angle, five point six
by five point six. Wild idea. רש״י Rashi says it just means
you need a square and again this last position, which is the
most consistent, says it means no when you measure to see if
you have רשות היחיד, reshut hayachid, you see if you have a
four by four square according based on the compass points. So if
you have something that's bigger than four by four but it's at
an angle and you could not fit in a four by four
square aligned to the compass points, it would not be a רשות
היחיד. reshut hayachid. So just wanted to repeat those because that's very
much you know not what we normally think and yesterday's דף daf
really sort of you know changed some basic assumptions. Yes Charlie.
So I've got a walled city and so outside of it according
to this thing I've got four אמות amot plus two thousand אמות.
amot.
No the four אמות amot does not start outside the walled city.
Oh okay. The walled city is your additional. Is it? First you
figure out your space and then it's two thousand אמות amot outside
of your space. So what's your space? If you're in a city
or if you're in a walled barn or house or whatever, your
space is the city or your space is the walled enclosure and
then two thousand אמות amot outside. If you're out in the middle
of a field, it's your four אמות amot is your space and
then it's two thousand אמות amot outside.
What does north mean to the people at the time of the
block?
How did they measure it?
I don't know. I mean they definitely spoke very I mean you
know the תורה Torah is always speaking about directions. I mean there's
the rising sun and the setting sun. Did they have but that
changes with the seasons.
Right. I don't know did they they didn't have when was the
whole idea of a magnetic compass and magnetic north figured out? Not
I guess then.
We've got it right now.
All right I don't know. Anyway you can all look it up
for the next what we're the next פרק perek which we're going
to start later today which is very much focuses on the compass
points when we figure out squaring off a city. Let's first finish
off this. מי שיצא לילך מעיר שמערבין בה. Mi sheyatzah leilech me'ir
sheme'arvin bah. Now this is quoted yesterday and here we'll get clarified
somewhat.
Somebody left a city that you
you know you would make an עירוב eruv from city A to
get to city B. And he was planning as we'll see in
the גמרא Gemara to go spend שבת Shabbos in city B. He
wasn't planning on making an עירוב, eruv, he was actually planning on
getting to city B before it got dark. והחזירו חברו Vehachiziro chaveiro
and his friend sort of you know sort of convinced him to
go back said oh it's too cold out tonight you know it's
too hot out tonight go back you'll go tomorrow. Okay so he
went back home to city A but he was still hoping to
go to city B tomorrow. So presumably he still now there's going
to be a discussion whether he verbally said designated a spot to
be his עירוב eruv or just we're assuming you know in his
mind. mind, obviously by him walking out and heading to City B,
implicitly it was clear he wanted to designate a particular spot to
be an עירוב. eruv. So he either verbally or implicitly had designated
a spot to be his עירוב eruv and then turned back home.
So הוא מותר ליה, hu mutar leh, he can go to City
B tomorrow, וכל בני העיר אסורים ve'chol bnei ha'ir assurim and everybody
of the rest of the city cannot. Now obviously it's pretty obvious
they cannot, they did not make an עירוב, eruv, but also as
we'll see in the גמרא Gemara what it means is even if
they had explicitly stayed home and said, yeah, yeah, yeah, we're planning
on going to City B and we want to designate the following
tree as our עירוב, eruv, it doesn't work. Why? Because this is
with what the גמרא Gemara quoted yesterday, this is the idea that
you're not physically present in a spot, you're just designating a distant
spot, you're not using bread, you're not physically present, and there we
said that both רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
agree that that only works for the עני, ani, only works for
the guy that didn't start off at home. So everybody in the
city is not an עני, ani, they are starting off at home,
they could use bread, they can't just sit in their easy chair
and designate some spot. This guy that was in the process of
traveling to City B and then he changed his mind and turned
around and went home, he's like the עני. ani. He's the guy
that's not considered starting from home because he's out there planning on
traveling. So for him, he was able to designate the spot even
though it was not the spot he was immediately present at. דברי
רבי יהודה, divrei Rabbi Yehuda, that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says.
רבי מאיר אומר Rabbi Meir omer כל שהוא יכול לערב ולא עירב,
kol she'hu yachol le'arev velo erev, anybody that could make an עירוב
eruv and didn't, like this guy, he could have gone there himself,
he could have used bread, maybe he's not considered an עני, ani,
he did ultimately leave City A, even though he was planning on
traveling, so maybe he's considered an עשיר, ashir, so הרי זה חמור
גמל, harei zeh chamor gamal, he is this famous donkey
driver camel puller, meaning he's being pulled in opposite directions, which basically
means, okay, now it's very, you'll see there's like a huge רש״י
Rashi because there's multiple ways of explaining what this debate is about.
But basically, right here City A, here City B, here's a tree,
let's say, and it's 2,000 אמות amot each way, right? So this
guy is walking and he's planning on going to City B for
שבת. Shabbat. But then his friend convinces him to go home. So
presumably we think that okay, but since he's planning the next morning
to go to B, at least he's thinking about making his עירוב
eruv under the tree, right? Because he's thinking, all right, I'll go
home, but I need to get to City B tomorrow, so either
he said or he's thinking to make his עירוב eruv under this
tree. But that is not physically present, right? That's making his עירוב
eruv at a distant spot where he's not there. But because he
on Friday afternoon was on a journey, was traveling, he's considered an
עני ani and he's entitled to designate it without being physically present.
Nobody in A sitting home in their easy chair can designate the
tree because they're all an עשיר ashir and they can't designate a
distant spot. Okay, so that's what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says it
actually works. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir said, no, I'm sorry, since he
tried to make it at this spot, but he wasn't able to.
Why not? Sounds like from רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir he says he
was יכול, yachol, that he could have done it himself, meaning he's
an עשיר, ashir, he started from house, he didn't really start traveling
from outside the city, so he's not able to do that, but
he tried to. So because he tried to, he gets the worst
of both worlds, which is this חמור גמל, chamor gamal, which means
he loses the benefit of starting here, right? So by starting here,
you have the benefit, you can travel 2,000 in this direction. So
he lost that benefit. On the other hand, he doesn't gain what
he gets by starting here because he wasn't really able to start
here because he was an עשיר. ashir. So therefore,
what's the only way he's able to travel? All he gets is
this 2,000 אמות. amot. Okay, so basically what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says is a simple way of understanding this is if you tried
to make an עירוב eruv and you didn't succeed, you have to,
you
lose what, you've given up what that עירוב eruv would have made
you give up. The cost of the 2,000 אמות amot is a
cost you pay by just trying to make the עירוב. eruv. So
you sacrificed the benefits of being in City A. So all you're
left, that's sort of the cost whether you succeed in making the
עירוב eruv or not. Okay, so that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
says, you're pulled in both directions, so you've lost the benefit of
being in A and all you get are those 2,000. Okay, so
that becomes an interesting position of רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that anybody
who tries to make an עירוב eruv and doesn't succeed for some
reason and רש״י Rashi says for example, let's say you put it
at a certain point and then you left and then before it
got dark, the עירוב eruv got eaten up or rolled away. That's
a simple example of you tried and you didn't succeed. רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir would say, okay, but once you tried, you gave up,
you have to pay the cost. The cost of doing an עירוב
eruv there is losing the distance in the other direction, that's a
distance you have to pay even if your עירוב eruv doesn't succeed
and all you're left with is so you're considered to have started
שבת Shabbat in the city because this עירוב eruv didn't succeed but
because you tried, right, so
what is it, no risk, no gain or something, anyway because you
tried, it's always going to cost you. the direction in the opposite
direction. That's רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position. Okay, so let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. Yes?
A general principle I also remember is if you're in a particular
location, you can travel two thousand אמות amos east, return to your
location, and then go west. Yes. We've accepted that as yes.
Two thousand אמות amos in every direction. Correct.
Because the point is that in the end this didn't work. If
it did work, you could get all the way to B. It
didn't work, so you really started at A.
But is there no principle of declaring your direction and then you're
stuck?
No, but there was an attempt to start שבת Shabbos here. So
based on what you were trying to do, you were prepared to
sacrifice any distance in this direction. So the attempt to do this
sacrificed your right to go to that direction. It's a strange idea.
He's kind of giving him a little bit of the עירוב. eruv.
Well, only the negative part of the עירוב, eruv,
not the positive part of the עירוב. eruv. Right. But he has
still the two thousand.
This two thousand he has because in the end this עירוב eruv
didn't work, so you wound up starting in A. So you do
have this two thousand based
on,
based on the fact that if your עירוב eruv didn't work, you
ultimately, you know, you live in city A, so
your עירוב eruv starts where you live. You're taking away part of
the benefit.
Yes, you're taking away the benefit, you know, the cost of making
the עירוב eruv would have been that, you always have to pay
that cost.
There's another way to say it, and that is that this is
the most conservative approach. You take the intersection of the two areas.
Yes, so that would be in a case of a ספק. safek.
Right. That would be in a case of ספק. safek. Right. We've
had that before. If it were a ספק, safek, right, if it
were a ספק, safek, then that's another way of explaining why you
get this because this is the overlap. But the reason I didn't
say that, that's one read of רש״י, Rashi, but based on the
language in the משנה Mishna and the language of the גמרא Gemara
on the עמוד ב, amud beis, the משנה Mishna is, if you
see it, it's not ספק. safek. It's כהוא שיכול לערב ולא עירב.
kehu sheyachol le'arev velo erev. Right? It's like, so it sounds like,
you know, you tried, you didn't succeed, here's the consequence. So yes,
one read of רש״י Rashi is that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir considers
it a ספק safek and that's why you get this middle amount.
But it's going to sound even more drastic to say that it's
not a ספק, safek, it's any failed attempt, that's the cost you
pay. Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. מאי שנא הוא
ומאי שנא אינהו? mai shna ihu u'mai shna inhu? So first says
the גמרא, Gemara, let's understand the beginning of the משנה. Mishna. Why
do you, the guy who went to city B, why are you
allowed to go all, you know, why does the עירוב eruv work
for you, it doesn't work for other people? So אמר רב הונא,
amar Rav Huna, הכא במאי עסקינן כשיש לו שני בתים וביניהם שני
תחומי שבת, hacha b'mai askinan k'sheyesh lo shnei batim u'beineihem shnei techumei
Shabbos, like the picture I drew you. You have a house in
city A, a house in city B, and they are four thousand
אמות amos apart with this tree in the middle. איהו, ihu, you,
כיון דנפיק ליה, keivan d'nafik lei, since you started on Friday to
spend שבת Shabbos in city B, כיון דנפיק ליה לאורחא, keivan d'nafik
lei l'orcha, you went out on your journey, הוי ליה עני. havei
lei ani. So you're not starting from home. It's not like you
went to the tree to put down the עירוב eruv from your
house. Then it's considered that the act of putting up the עירוב
eruv began at home. No, you began a journey and then you
sort of decided in the middle to make an עירוב. eruv. So
you were starting outside of the house. That makes you an עני.
ani. So והני, v'hanei, and everybody else, עשירי נינהו. ashiri ninhu. Everybody
else who's in city A are rich, they're all in their home.
So therefore they cannot designate a distant spot. But you are able
to designate a different spot. Okay. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi,
we taught similarly, מי שיש לו שני בתים וביניהם שני תחומי שבת,
mi sheyesh lo shnei batim u'beineihem shnei techumei Shabbos, saying exact, describe
the way we did. House in A and house in B. כיון
שהחזיק בדרך, keivan she'hechezik baderech, once you החזיק בדרך, hechezik baderech, meaning
you started your journey, קנה עירוב דברי רבי יהודה. kana eruv divrei
Rabbi Yehuda. So therefore your עירוב eruv works because now you're considered
to be out on the, on a journey. You're not considered to
have begun putting the, act of putting the עירוב eruv does not
begin at your home, it begins from the journey, and therefore it
works. יתר על כן אמר רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה. yaser al ken
amar Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Yehuda. Now רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yosi, the son
of רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, went even one step further and he
said, אפילו מצאו חבירו ואמר לו לין פה, afilu matza'o chaveiro v'amar
lo lin po, even if your friend said, found you and said
to you, you know what, don't bother going, don't go tonight, sleep
here. אש חמה הוא, eish chama hu, it's hot outside. אש צינה
הוא, eish tzina hu, it's cold outside. So your friend turned you
around and made you go home. למחר, lemachar, the next morning, משכים
והולך, mashkim v'holech, you can go and do it. Now what do
you mean יתר על כן? yaser al ken? First of all, that's
what the משנה Mishna said. The משנה Mishna was that scenario. Number
two is why is that a חידוש chiddush more than רבי יהודה?
Rabbi Yehuda? You wanted to go, you turned around, you stayed home,
how is that any different than what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda said?
So the גמרא's Gemara going to give two interpretations of the debate.
אמר רבא, amar Rava,
לומר, lomar, the idea of saying, כולי עלמא לא פליגי דצריך. kuli
alma lo pligi d'tzarich. Everybody agrees that that's a necessary component of
allowing you to do this. What is saying, you know, I'll explain
in a minute. כי פליגי, ki pligi, what's the debate, meaning between
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi
Yehuda, להחזיק, lehachzik, whether you actually have to start your journey. Meaning
so what he says is is that when רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yosi b'Rabbi Yehuda says the guy tells you sleep here whatever,
that's not a חידוש. chiddush. That would be the same scenario for
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. The difference is is that where רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda said מי שהחזיק, mi she'hechezik, כיון שהחזיק בדרך, keivan she'hechezik
baderech, once you began, once you left the house and started your
journey, that's when you're defined as an
עני. ani. Meaning your friend found you at home, you were talking
about going to see your daughter in the next city and your
friend said, you know what, do it tomorrow. Okay, so according to
רבה Rabbah the debate is as whether you have to in this
idea of becoming an עני oni which entitles you to designate a
distant space, according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you have to actually
take the first step out of your house, החזיק בדרך. hechzik ba-derech.
Right, what's the Chinese proverb, journey of a thousand miles begins with
a single step? So according to רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you have
to take the single step at least, you have to step out
of your house. And according to רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose
be-Rabbi Yehuda it's even if your friend found you in your house,
even if you were just planning, that is enough makes you consider
to be an עני. oni. Big חידוש. chiddush. Now what's the idea
of לומר? lomar? You need to say something. So רש"י Rashi has
two interpretations. I'm going to give the second, I'll tell you both,
I'm going to focus on the second one. The first interpretation is
more sort of works better in the text of the גמרא. Gemara.
It means whether the friend has to tell you turn around and
you know it's too cold, it's too hot, stay home. If you
decided on your own you stop being an עני oni because then
you've like changed your mind, you're no longer somebody who wants to
be going, you've completely changed your mind. So that's the question whether
the turning around is on your own decision or because somebody persuaded
you. So that's the question of whether of that as a necessary
component. But the better explanation or more logical one even if it
doesn't work so much textually
is, what's missing in this scenario, even if we call you an
עני oni and you're able to designate a distant space, is that
you didn't say anything, you didn't designate the space. The משנה Mishnah
doesn't talk about designating the space, right? And even if we could
imagine, well, obviously you wanted to, but the whole previous משנה Mishnah
said you have to be very specific, right? You couldn't say somewhere
by the wall, somewhere by the tree. So now we're going to
read your mind and figure out exactly where you wanted to do
it? No. So therefore everybody agrees you have to verbally designate the
space. That's what רש"י Rashi says, not the לומר lomar that's in
the way it's being described about your friend convincing you. No, you
have to verbally designate the space. Everybody agrees to that. The only
question is, are you an עני oni or not? Have you begun
your journey or not? רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you have to
begin your journey and רבי יוסי Rabbi Yose says even if you
were just planning on taking the journey, that's enough to make you
an עני. oni. Okay so that's the debate. Now we go, that's
what רבה Rabbah said. רב יוסף אמר, Rav Yosef amar, now רב
יוסף Rav Yosef says different. להחזיק, le-hachzik, to begin your journey, דכולי
עלמא לא פליגי דצריך. du-kulei alma lo pligi de-tzarich. If you want
to get this status of an עני, oni, everybody agrees that you
have to actually step out of your house, so you're not considered
as starting from home. כי פליגי, ki pligi,
so what's the debate of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי יוסי,
Rabbi Yose, רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, לומר, lomar, whether again I'm going
to read it the second way of רש"י, Rashi, whether you have
to designate. So therefore רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda would say you have
to designate, and רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda would
say again it's not really in the words, רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda would say that no, even if you didn't
designate, you know, it's so yes you have to start your journey
but we can read your mind and you don't have to actually
verbally designate. Okay so this then is the debate. Do you need
to, you can argue there are two components here: you have to
begin your journey to be an עני oni and you have to
designate or not designate or are we trying to read your mind?
Okay. So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda presumably requires both, starting your journey
and designating, and the question is what does רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה
Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda say? One or the other, and that's debated
between רבה Rabbah and רב יוסף. Rav Yosef. So let's take a
look.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this, כמאן אזלא הא דאמר עולא?
ke-man azla ha de-amar Ulla? Who's it going like that which עולא
Ulla said? מי שהחזיק בדרך והחזירו חבירו. mi she-hechzik ba-derech ve-hecheziru chaveiro.
You started your journey and your friend persuaded you to turn around
and go home. הרי הוא מותר ומחזר ומחזק. harei hu mutar u-muchzar
u-muchzak. You are returned home and established in your new place. So
the גמרא Gemara says, what does that mean? אי מחזר, ee muchzar,
if you're considered to be turned back around, so you're no longer
a special case, למה מחזק? lamah muchzak? Why are you entitled to
the new space for the עירוב? eruv? You're just like anybody else
in the city. ואי מחזק, ve-ee muchzak, if you are entitled to
the new space of the עירוב, eruv, למה מחזר? lamah muchzar? Why
are you considered turned back around? Now מחזק muchzak could also by
the way mean החזיק בדרך hechzik ba-derech also, which is probably a
better read, right? Because that's the phrase of מחזק. muchzak. So if
you're turned around, why are you considered to still be on your
journey? And if you're still on your journey and you know, why
are you considered to be turned around? How did you say you're
both turned around and on your journey? So the גמרא Gemara says,
הכי קאמר, hachi ka-amar, here's what it means. אף על פי שמחזר
מחזק. af-al-pi she-muchzar muchzak. Even though you are turned around, you still
are on your journey or maybe again or your עירוב eruv works.
So כמאן, ke-man, who is that idea like? כרב יוסף אליבא דרבי
יוסי ברבי יהודה. ke-Rav Yosef aliba de-Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda. That's like
רב יוסף'ס Rav Yosef's read of רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה, Rabbi Yose
be-Rabbi Yehuda, meaning because רב יוסף Rav Yosef said that everybody agrees
you need, what do you call it, you need to start the
journey, but רבי יוסי ברבי יהודה Rabbi Yose be-Rabbi Yehuda says you
don't have to verbally designate. So the assumption here is that since
it says you're מחזק, muchzak, you're turned around, somehow there's an assumption
that this statement of עולא Ulla suggests So there we're describing a
scenario where you actually started your journey החזיק hechehzikh and it works
even though you are מוחזר mukhzar even though you didn't say a
word. Okay
so that is who's that idea that you can start your journey
you need to start your journey but you don't need to say
a word? That's the way רב יוסף Rav Yosef explained רב יוסי
ברבי יהודה. Rav Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda. So again if this is getting
a little confusing basically I'll say it one more time. According to
everybody רבא Rava and this is only one read of רש"י Rashi
there's two other reads. First read of רש"י Rashi read of תוספות
Tosafot there's a lot of possibilities. I'm simplifying it. According to this
one read of רש"י Rashi okay everybody agrees that according to רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda you need two things to step out of the
house and to verbally designate. Both of those make sense to be
an עני ani and then to know where you're starting it. What
does רב יוסי ברבי יהודה Rav Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda hold? That's debated.
רבא Rava says he holds you need to verbally designate but you
don't need to step out of your house and רב יוסף Rav
Yosef says you need to step out of your house but you
don't need to verbally designate. So he holds one of the criteria
not the other. We've just read this statement of עולא Ula which
the גמרא Gemara is somehow interpreting—not exactly clear why it's interpreting—interpreting to
mean that you had to step out of your house but you
didn't have to verbally designate. Who is that like? That's like רב
יוסף's Rav Yosef read of רב יוסי ברבי יהודה. Rav Yose b'Rabbi
Yehuda. The only criteria that matters is stepping out of your house.
Okay so now the גמרא Gemara says like this: רב יהודה בר
אשתתא Rav Yehuda bar Ishtata אייתי ליה קלדא דפירי aytei leh kalda
d'firi to רב נתן בר אושעיא. Rav Natan bar Oshaya. So רב
יהודה בר אשתתא Rav Yehuda bar Ishtata name of some person brought
a basket of fruit to רב נתן בר אושעיא Rav Natan bar
Oshaya on like ערב שבת Erev Shabbat you know and then he
was turning around and he had to go back home. Okay so
he was trying to get back home to whatever his other city
before it got dark. כי הוה אזיל Ki hava azil as he
was leaving this רב יהודה בר אשתתא Rav Yehuda bar Ishtata שבקיה
shavkei so רב נתן בר אושעיא Rav Natan bar Oshaya you know
very consciously waited עד דנחית דרגא ad d'nachit darga until he took
one step out of the room. Like went one step down—he was
in an attic a second floor and took one step down on
the stairwell. So that's החזיק בדרך hechehzikh baderekh right because he left
the room and he started now to leave to go back home.
אמר ליה Amar leh and as soon as he took one step
down he said ביתך. Beitkha. You know what? Sleep here tonight. למחר
קדים ואזיל L'machar kadim v'azil you'll go tomorrow on שבת Shabbat day
itself. Okay so that was exactly the scenario of the משנה: Mishna:
החזיק בדרך hechehzikh baderekh and he turned him around. Okay of course
the interesting thing there also is it sounds like there was no
verbal designation right of the spot? Yes right? I mean the whole
thing was being manipulated by רב נחמן בר יצחק. Rav Nachman bar
Yitzchak. So the גמרא Gemara says כמאן? K'man? Who is that going
like? Again to רב יוסף Rav Yosef באליבא דרב יוסי ברבי יהודה
b'aliba d'Rav Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda like רב יוסף Rav Yosef according to
רב יוסי ברבי יהודה Rav Yose b'Rabbi Yehuda that says you need
to start the journey so he waited till he took a step
out of the house but you don't need any verbal designation. And
then the גמרא Gemara says and this is a hard again to
read according to this approach: לא כרבא ובאליבא דרבי יהודה. Lo k'Rava
v'aliba d'Rabbi Yehuda. No it's like רבא Rava according to רבי יהודה
Rabbi Yehuda which is strange because according to this reading of רש"י
Rashi that requires both things: leaving and designating. So רש"י Rashi says
what the גמרא Gemara means is how do you know he didn't
designate? Maybe when he said stay here tonight he said and designate
such and such a space to be for your עירוב. eruv. Okay
so in the end though we have that this is a nice
elaboration of the previous משנה. Mishna. Yeah that you're allowed to designate
a distant space. What we are saying now is whatever the debate
of רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir was about
whether it had to be poor or not poor that was when
you're in the space that you're standing. Designating a distant space everybody
agrees you have to be poor but poor for this purpose is
a special allowance. I would also remind you that the previous גמרא
Gemara said also only if you pre-guess that space before it gets
dark. And that special allowance is only for somebody that's poor at
a distant space and poor meaning that you did not start שבת
Shabbat at home you did not start your putting of the עירוב
eruv from home. If you started from home the process of putting
the עירוב eruv you're not considered poor. So if a guy's on
the way and then decides to make an עירוב eruv that's where
he is allowed to do it. What's defined as on the way?
Taking one step out of the house according to רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda and again then he would and there's a debate whether he
has to verbally designate. I have to tell you again it's very
strange to think he doesn't have to verbally designate A to think
that we can read his mind but B not just read his
mind that he wants to go to city B but read his
mind to define exactly where he wants to start his שבת Shabbat
because all the discussion until this point had been about the need
to precisely define. So to think that you don't have to designate
is quite strange. Okay now the גמרא Gemara goes to wrap up
this משנה Mishna with the position of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir who
says you only get the overlap or you have to pay the
cost. Okay so it is correct that one way to read this
משנה Mishna is that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says it's a ספק
safek if it works and I'm only giving you the overlap. But
now we'll see why I did not read the משנה Mishna that
way. רבי מאיר אמר כל שיכול לערב. Rabbi Meir amar kol sheyakhol
l'arev. So the גמרא Gemara says
התנינא חדא זימנא. Hatanina chada zimna. This idea that you're pulled in
both ways we've already taught in the name of רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. What did we teach? ספק. Safek. This was an earlier משנה
Mishna that you put your עירוב eruv outside of the city at
your two thousand marker and then it got destroyed. Or rolled away.
But you don't know whether that happened on שבת Shabbos or before
שבת, Shabbos, right? It happened בין השמשות. bein hashmashos. So you don't
know whether the עירוב Eiruv was effective or not. So that's a
case of a ספק עירוב. safeik eiruv. רבי מאיר ורבי יהודה אומרים
Rabbi Meir v'Rabbi Yehuda Omrim הרי זה חמור גמל. harei zeh chamor
gamal. So in that case where it's a ספק, safeik, you only
get the overlap. Okay? So that is a very, that's a very
straightforward case, right? Here you are, right, you put your עירוב eiruv
over here, right, at 2000 אמות, amos, then it gets destroyed, okay,
or rolls away. You don't know if it worked. So you don't
know if it worked, so if it did work, you get these
2000, if it didn't work, you get those 2000, so you take,
right, the intersection. That would be the scenario if it didn't work,
this would be the scenario if it did work, so all you
get is the middle 2000. So that's the case of an earlier
משנה, mishna, it's a ספק safeik if it worked. So why do
you have to tell me here as well? So the גמרא Gemara
says, now then, now we're going to see why I read the
משנה mishna differently, I mean I was following רש"י. Rashi. So the
גמרא Gemara says, אמר רב ששת, Amar Rav Sheshet, לא תימא טעמא
דרבי מאיר ספק עירב ספק לא עירב הוא דהוי חמור גמל. lo
teima ta'ama d'Rabbi Meir safeik eireiv safeik lo eireiv hu d'havei chamor
gamal. Don't say according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir it's only when
there's a doubt if it worked, then you're pulled in both directions
and you get the overlap. אבל ודאי לא עירב, Aval vadai lo
eireiv, if it definitely did not work, לא הוי חמור גמל, lo
havei chamor gamal, you would not do this idea of pulled in
both directions. אלא אפילו ודאי לא עירב, Ella afilu vadai lo eireiv,
even if it definitely did not work, הוי חמור גמל, havei chamor
gamal, you're pulled in both directions, דהכא ודאי לא עירב. d'hacha vadai
lo eireiv. The language of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir reflects the idea
that he understands that this guy on the journey definitely did not
work. The guy on the journey according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
from city A to B would be considered an עשיר, ashir, not
an עני, oni, because he started, leaving his house at A, and
it was definitely not effective, וקהוי חמור גמל, ve'kahavei chamor gamal, and
nevertheless he only gets the overlap, he gets the cross. So that's
why following רש"י Rashi and the language of the משנה mishna was
the same. Like the language of the משנה mishna was כל שהוא
יכול לערב ולא עירב. kol shehu yachol l'areiv v'lo eireiv. He doesn't
say any case that's a ספק. safeik. Any case that you were,
you could have and it wasn't effective, is the way רש"י's Rashi
reading it, you are a חמור גמל. chamor gamal. So basically, according
to the way רש"י Rashi says, in this scenario, even if it
wasn't a ספק, safeik, even if you knew that the עירוב eiruv
rolled away before שבת Shabbos began, since you tried to put the
עירוב eiruv here, you already have to, sort of, sacrifice this, this.
You were trying to do this, the cost was the going in
the opposite directions. So even if it definitely did not work, you're
only left with those 2000 אמות. amos.
Okay, there's always a cost for trying to put an עירוב. eiruv.
It's a pretty harsh understanding.
I'm sorry, Charlie?
That's according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir.
That's רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, yeah, we wouldn't rule that way. Alright,
so now, now we continue. מי שיצא, Mi sheyatza,
and this actually parallels some of the opening משניות. mishnayot. The opening
משניות mishnayot were the guy that walked outside of the תחום, techum,
he only has four אמות. amot. If he went out of the
תחום techum for a מצוה, mitzvah, he has 2000 אמות, amos, etc.,
etc. So, מי שיצא חוץ לתחום, mi sheyatza chutz l'techum,
and we've quoted this משנה mishna before, when is this idea that
you're considered to have left the תחום, techum, and that you're limited
to four אמות? amot? אפילו אמה אחת, Afilu ama achat, even if
you take one overstep, לא יכנס, lo yikanes, you cannot go back
in, and you only have four אמות. amot. רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi
Eliezer omer שתים יכול ליכנס שלש לא יכנס. shtayim yachol l'ikanes shalosh
lo yikanes. No, you're actually given two extra אמות. amos. So this
is actually interesting, for we had
this spoke our 2000 became 2004 and now it's becoming 2006. Right,
because here we're saying you're here, again if you're a city you
get the whole city. But we're now saying you get four אמות,
amot, okay, I don't know 4x4 or 2x2. Then you get your
2000, and here's your
marker. And now you took a step or two out, so you're
in this zone. So comes along רבי אליעזר, Rabbi Eliezer, so the
חכמים chachamim say, oh, you overstepped the line, you're stuck. רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says no, because when you overstep the line, what do
we at least give you as soon as you overstep the line?
We give you four אמות, amot, which he says two in each
direction. So therefore as long as you're within two, if you've only
overstepped up to two, your new four אמות amot overlap the 2000
and therefore you are able to step back in because of that
overlap. And the חכמים chachamim say no, even if now they overlap,
you overstepped the line and you're stuck. So let's take a look
at what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר רבי חנינא Amar Rabbi Hanina
רגלו אחת בתוך התחום רגלו אחת חוץ לתחום. reglo achat betoch hatechum
reglo achat chutz latechum. If you have one foot in and one
foot
out. The גמרא Gemara does this once with a chicken that's found
out a 50 אמה ama line, a question about whose chicken it
is. Anyway, you have one foot in the תחום techum and one
foot out. So this is according to the חכמים chachamim that even
one step outside, you lose the תחום. techum. So לא יכנס, lo
yikanes, you can't go back in, so you can't pull your other
foot back in. Or presumably then you have four אמות amot from
where you're standing, but you've lost your תחום. techum. Okay, why? דכתיב,
de'chtiv, because the פסוק pasuk says, again interestingly quoting a פסוק pasuk
for these
rabbinic laws, אם תשיב משבת רגלך. im tashiv mishabbat raglecha. your שבת.
shabbat. So רגלך raglecha כתיב. ktiv. It says רגלך raglecha singular. So
therefore there's a time where even your one foot has to be
stopped from going back, even one foot out makes you it's considered
to have been crossed the line. So the גמרא gemara says ובתניא
רגלו אחת בתוך התחום ורגלו אחת חוץ לתחום יכנס. vatan'ya raglo achat
betoch hatchum veraglo achat chutz latchum yikanes. If your one foot's in
and one foot out, you can go back. That's not yet that
you fully stepped over the line. So the גמרא gemara says הא
מני אחרים היא. ha manni acherim hi. Okay, that's according to a
different opinion. There's a ברייתא braita of אחרים acherim that דתניא detanya
we've done a ברייתא braita אחרים אומרים acherim omrim others say למקום
שרובו הוא נזדקר lemakom sherubo hu nizdaker where the majority of you
are, you're thrown towards that. So even if you're one step out,
somehow it seems that that's only one leg of you and it
seemed like I guess even if you're leaning, it still seemed that
your basic weight is supported behind you and you are mostly still
within the תחום, techum, so you're fine. איכא דאמרי ika de'amri others
say אמר רבי חנינא amar Rabbi Chanina רגלו אחת בתוך התחום ורגלו
אחת חוץ לתחום יכנס raglo achat betoch hatchum veraglo achat chutz latchum
yikanes that actually he Rabbi Chanina said like this אחרים acherim that
you can go back in. דכתיב dichtiv why אם תשיב משבת רגלך
im tashiv mishabbat raglecha רגליך קרינן. raglayich karinan. We read it רגליך.
raglayich. Now we don't read it רגליך, raglayich, we read it רגלך.
raglecha. So I don't exactly get that, but anyway he somehow says
that that פסוק pasuk means only when it's two feet that you
have to stop. But if you only have to stop one foot,
you're allowed to bring it back in. Okay? So the גמרא gemara
says ובתניא לא יכנס. vatan'ya lo yikanes. But one minute, the ברייתא
braita says you can't. הוא דאמר כאחרים hu de'amar ke'acherim so Rabbi
Chanina goes like the אחרים acherim דתניא detanya למקום שרובו נזדקר lemakom
sherubo nizdaker because we just quoted before אחרים acherim say you go
where the majority of you are is. So therefore your weight and
your basic body is still behind the line. So this is according
to the חכמים chachamim that one step over the line, you're outside
the תחום techum and the question is what about a half step,
what about one leg, and with the Rabbi Chanina saying then you're
still... two opinions about what Rabbi Chanina would say. Now רבי אליעזר
אומר שתים יכנס שלש לא יכנס Rabbi Eliezer omer shtayim yikanes shalosh
lo yikanes up to two אמות amot over the line you can
still go back in because then your new four אמות amot overlap.
So the גמרא gemara says ובתניא רבי אליעזר אומר אחת יכנס שתים
לא יכנס vatan'ya Rabbi Eliezer omer achat yikanes shtayim lo yikanes one
אמה amah outside you can go in, two you can't. גמרא gemara
says לא קשיא. lo kashya. It's not difficult. הא דעקר חדא וקמה
תרתי ha de'akar chada vekama tarti when does it say when does
it say two you can go back? It means you're in the
second אמה. amah. You left the first אמה amah and you're within
the second. So if you're within the second אמה, amah, you can
go back. When it says הא דעקר תרתי וקמה תלת ha de'akar
tarti vekama tlat when it says you can't go back after two,
it means that you've left two אמות. amot. הא דעקר תרתי ha
de'akar tarti when you've actually left the two אמה amah line וקמה
תלת vekama tlat and you're in the third אמה amah you cannot
go back. Okay, so one says you can go back up to
two אמות amot and the other says you know you can go
once you have gone two אמות amot or more outside of it,
you can no longer go back. Okay, so the גמרא gemara says
now ובתניא רבי אליעזר אומר אפילו אמה אחת לא יכנס. vatan'ya Rabbi
Eliezer omer afilu amah achat lo yikanes.
We have a ברייתא braita that Rabbi Eliezer says just like the
חכמים chachamim even one אמה amah you cannot go back. That's clearly
a contradiction to our משנה. mishna. So כי תניא
ההיא למודד. ki tanya hahi lemoded. No, no, no, that's not talking
about the guy that stepped over the line. If you stepped over
the line, you still get two אמות. amot. This is talking about
about your about when you are measuring and you reach the end
of your line. What does it mean? דתנן detnan ולמודד שאמרו נותנים
לו אלפים אמה אפילו סוף מדתו כלה במערה. ulemoded she'amru notnim lo
alpayim amah afilu sof midato kala beme'arah.
So the one who measures, we give him the two thousand אמות
amot even if he if it ends in the middle of a
cave. Which means what? There's one case which is בדיעבד. bedi'avad. You
stepped over the line. בדיעבד bedi'avad you stepped over the line, he
says if you're still within two אמות amot you can get back.
But let's say here you are, this is the city, okay, and
you find yourself outside of the city as it's getting to be
dark, okay, and you're stuck out here for שבת. shabbat. So what
do you do? So it says you measure, you count off two
thousand paces. That's what it means מודד. moded. You're a measurer. You
count off two thousand paces from where you were and you ended
right here. Now when you start in the city, you get the
whole city plus two thousand אמות. amot. But when you start outside
the city, right, then your two thousand אמות amot ends wherever it
ends. So when your two thousand אמות amot ends here, that's it.
You can't take even one step further. Even if you're in a
city and even if you're in the middle of a cave, even
if that's got you inside of a house, here you are, you
walked into a house, okay, you have to stop exactly at that
two thousand אמה amah line. So when when do you get the
house or the city plus two thousand when you start inside? When
you start outside, you end where you end. So the ברייתא braita
that Rabbi Eliezer says you can't even step one אמה amah out
is this scenario. You're not allowed to step over the line even
if you end in a city or end in a house. Here
he's talking בדיעבד. bedi'avad. You did step over the line. Oh, you
did step over the line, then you have two אמות amot if
and if you have two אמות amot you can get back in.
Okay? So in one way of seeing it, it's just a לכתחילה
בדיעבד. lechatchila bedi'avad. You know, לכתחילה lechatchila don't step over the line.
בדיעבד bedi'avad you can step back. But this is a bigger חידוש.
chidush. Because it's even if you wind up ending in a city
or a house, you still cannot take one more step.
Okay, last משנה *Mishna*, מי שהוציאו חוץ לתחום *Mi shehotzi'u chutz latchum*,
אפילו אמה אחת לא יכנס *afilu ama achas lo yicanes*. Now, if
you are, it got dark for you outside of the תחום *tchum*,
even one אמה *ama* you're outside of the, like, תחום *tchum* of
the city, then you cannot go back, go in. Now what does
it mean you can't go back in? I mean you have two
thousand אמות *amot* from where you are. So the way the רמב״ם
*Rambam* reads this and I think the simplest way is basically exactly
this scenario. Let's say you, it got dark for you outside of
the city, you found yourself on the road outside of the city,
and your two thousand אמה *ama* ends right before the city limits.
Okay? In that case, you cannot get into the city. If it
ends right before your house, you're stuck with your two thousand אמות
*amot*, you can't say, oh, I almost got there. Okay, so even
one אמה *ama* outside, don't go into the city or don't go
into your house. רבי שמעון אומר *Rabbi Shimon omer*, אפילו חמש עשרה
אמה יכנס *afilu chamesh esrei ama yicanes*. You know what? You actually
have fifteen extra אמות *amot*. Why do you have fifteen extra אמות
*amot*? Okay, שאין המשוכות ממציאות את המידות מפני הטועים *she'ein hamshuchot mamtzi'ot
et hamidot mipnei hato'im*. Because the measurers don't exactly measure the distance,
they are intentionally imprecise because people make a mistake. So they put
like some people set their watches intentionally fast, okay, because they know
they're always going to be late. So even though at some level
they know their watch is set fast, the fact that when they
get up and it says seven o'clock, you know, or seven ten,
that makes them go a little bit faster. So here he's saying
actually the measures are off and you actually have an extra fifteen
אמה *ama* from where the boundaries are.
So if outside of the city, like they put a marker and
they
say basically, here ends תחום שבת *tchum Shabbat*, okay, and they have
these markers outside of the city, you actually, and you find yourself
ערב שבת *erev Shabbat* a few steps before outside of the marker,
you're still within the תחום *tchum*. Because actually it is, their markers
are placed fifteen אמה *ama* right prior to the real end of
שבת *Shabbat*. So if you found yourself right, right over here when
שבת *Shabbat* began, you still are, if you're within fifteen, the same
way here we had a buffer of two, you're still within the,
you really are starting שבת *Shabbat* within the תחום *tchum* and you
are okay. תנא *Tana*, the גמרא *Gemara* says, מפני טועי המידה *mipnei
to'ei hamida*, because of the mistakes of the measure. Now it does
also say מפני *mipnei*, so the mistakes of the, meaning of people
that will, so who are the טועים *to'im*? So it could be
the טועים *to'im* the people that are themselves outside of the city
will make a mistake and therefore, you know, they won't pay attention
to the marker and you give them a little buffer zone. But
רש״י *Rashi*, I should say, has another explanation which is why it's
exactly fifteen אמה *ama*. Because the גמרא *Gemara* says you use a
rope of fifty אמה *ama* to measure off the two thousand. Now
that rope, I hold one end, you hold an end, and we
stand and we hold it tight, and that's fifty אמה *ama*. But
if that's true, how many, how many measures of fifty אמה *ama*
do we have to do to make two thousand? Forty. But each
one of us while we're holding the rope is holding on with
part of the rope. So we're not actually measuring a full fifty.
We're measuring minus a טפח *tefach*, right? This is a טפח *tefach*.
So if you multiply forty times two טפחים tfachim *tefachim*, because my
טפח *tefach* and your טפח *tefach*, is eighty טפחים *tefachim*, okay, and
there's six טפחים *tefachim* per, what do you call it, per אמה
*ama*, so it's almost fifteen. It would be fifteen if it was
ninety. So right, you see that? Ninety טפחים *tefachim*. So רש״י *Rashi*
says, okay, it's like a טפח *tefach* and a finger, I don't
know why a finger, like a little bit. You do the math
and if you subtract every measure a little bit more than two
טפחים *tefachim*, in the end we're off by fifteen אמות *amot*. So
therefore you get, everybody gets a buffer of fifteen אמות *amot* that
they're not yet outside the תחום *tchum* of the city. Okay. הדרן
עלך מי שהוציאוהו *Hadran alach Mi shehotzi'uhu*. Now we begin the next
פרק *perek*, which is I think a real fun one. First of
all there's going to be a lot of אגדתות *aggadot*, so that'll
be fun. But anyway, it's fun because we're going to look at
maps and we're going to figure out how to, how to
actually measure the תחום *tchum* of a city. Okay? And this is
the whole idea of, of what do you call it, this is
the whole idea of, you know, of going by the, נו *nu*,
of going by the, going by the compass. So I'm trying to
look at my picture here of Google here to take a look
at what Manhattan looks like. Yeah, it's pretty much a forty-five degree
angle, right, Manhattan. So if you think about it, right, it's something
like, I don't know, ציור *tziyur*, I don't know, something like this.
It looks a little like this ציור *tziyur*.
Anyway, by the way, I looked up magnetic compasses, they were not
used for navigation until the Middle Ages.
Okay, but the stars.
They definitely
used the North Star to do North.
Okay,
so they were able to figure out due North based on the
North Star, at least at night,
as navigation took place long before.
Right. Okay, so let's take a look at the משנה *Mishna*. כיצד
מעברין את הערים *Keitzad me'abrin et ha'arim*. Now though
that's of course all about עירובין *Eruvin*, but this is the word
מעברין *me'abrin* from עובר *ubar*, right, מעוברת *me'uberet*, pregnant. So how do
you sort of give the city a little bit of its expanded
space? Okay, that's what it means. So how do you sort of
give the city some of its expanded space? So before we get
to the compass idea, part of the idea we're going to deal
with is that it's got all these bumps, and we've got to
square off those bumps. So how do you do that? Okay?
So בית נכנס בית יוצא, some you know houses go a little
outside the wall or inside the wall. It doesn't make a nice
straight line. Okay. פגם נכנס פגם יוצא, Pogum nichnas pogum yotzei, or
some indent indented part. Again, a crescent part. Does it mean of
the wall? Does it mean Rashi says of like maybe a castle
or a turret or whatever? Anyways, goes in and out. It's not
straight lines, right? It's jagged lines. היו שם גדודיות גבוהות עשרה טפחים.
Hayu sham gedudiyot gvohot asara tfachim.
Let's say there were Rashi says this means like destroyed houses, but
they were still ten טפחים high. Okay, now all of these things,
what's considered to be part of the city has to be spaces
that are inhabited. So even though we're talking about a destroyed house,
we'll see whatever that there's some sense about people still living there.
וגשרים, Ugesharim, or there are bridges. ונפשות, Unefashot, which are basically like
tombstones or other types of structures in the cemetery. שיש בהן בית
דירה. Sheyesh bahen beit dira. Now this, this is presumably referring to
all the things we just mentioned, because every, what defines it as
still a part of the city is that there's some sense of
its being inhabited. So all these things have some type of a
habitation connected to them. Like by the tombstones, the idea is that
the guard of the cemetery has a little booth where he sleeps
in his booth and he watches in his booth and so on,
and therefore that's still considered an inhabited space. Right? Being inhabited by
the dead bodies doesn't count. Okay, so all these spaces, first you
have to figure out what are the parameters of the city. Right?
You know, where, what are the last, what are the points that
you mark? So you have to mark the most distant points that
there is some habitation. Okay, here's your city, right? And you know,
you have a lot of houses here, whatever, and you have a
cemetery here, and you have a bridge here, whatever. Anyway, so all
the places where some, there's some, something that people live to attached
to, you know, gets counted as the points, and you sort of,
you know, you sort of define the points that are at the
outskirts of the city based on the most distant places where people
are living. מוציאין את המדה כנגדן, Motzi'in et hamida kenegdan, so you
extend the line, the measuring line, opposite where these most distant inhabited
places are.
ועושין אותה כמין טבלא מרובעת, Ve'osin ota kemin tablo meruba'at, and this
becomes the really key point. After you now know the points of
the city, you make a square טבלא tablo כדי שנשתכר את הזויות,
Kedei shenishtaker et hazaviyot, so you should benefit the corners. So according
to this, right, if we take a look at Manhattan, okay, so
first of all, like, it's all inhabited, right? But according to this,
I don't know, if there was let's say, I don't know, let's
say this was the northernmost point, or the easternmost point, and there
was a cemetery here, right? So you wouldn't be able to include
that cemetery. You'd have to find some other easternmost point unless somebody
was lived in like a little house by the cemetery, and then
it would. So you find all of the points, you find this
and this and this. Now, you could say making it a square
just means, you know, squaring it off, you know, like that, right?
So you take whatever it is, meaning you make the some type
of a, of a rectangle that it fits into, that you know
the furthest points are hitting the edges of the rectangle. But if
you're going to do it based on the compass points, you're going
to get a much bigger city, right? Because it's going to wind
up looking like this. Okay?
So the question is
do you just square it off, or do you square it off
according to the compass points? And we actually פוסקין poskin you square
it off according to the compass points. So we will continue looking
at this tomorrow. Okay?